Why did <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION> award a <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> contract to a tiny <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION> company?

Rebuilding <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>’s electricity system after <PERSON>Hurricane Maria</PERSON> will be a massive task, but <NUMBER>one</NUMBER> of <LOCATION>America</LOCATION>’s smallest utility companies has been chosen to do it. As The <ORGANIZATION>Washington Post</ORGANIZATION> reported on <DATE>Monday</DATE>, the largest government contract awarded so far in the relief effort has gone to <ORGANIZATION>Whitefish Energy</ORGANIZATION>, a <DURATION>two-year-old</DURATION> company based in <LOCATION>Montana</LOCATION>. <LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION> had only <NUMBER>two</NUMBER> full-time employees when <PERSON>Maria</PERSON> struck <DATE>a month ago</DATE>, but <DATE>now</DATE> has been entrusted with a <MONEY>$300 million</MONEY> contract to “repair and reconstruct large portions of the island’s electrical infrastructure.”

To those concerned that such a tiny company is charged with restoring electricity to more than <NUMBER>three million</NUMBER> people, <LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION> offers this explanation: Its business model “calls for ramping up rapidly by hiring workers on short-term contracts.” <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>’s power authority also said <LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION> was the <ORDINAL>first</ORDINAL> company “available to arrive and they were the ones that <ORDINAL>first</ORDINAL> accepted terms and conditions” from the authority. The company also has “expertise in mountainous areas.”

<LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION> also happens to be primarily financed by a large donor to President <PERSON>Donald Trump</PERSON>. As The <SET>Daily</SET> Beast reported on <DATE>Tuesday</DATE>, <LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION> gets its money from a private equity firm called <ORGANIZATION>HBC Investments</ORGANIZATION>. Its founder, <PERSON>Joe Colonnetta</PERSON>, “contributed <MONEY>$20,000</MONEY> to the <ORGANIZATION>Trump Victory PAC</ORGANIZATION> during the general election, <MONEY>$27,000</MONEY> to <PERSON>Trump</PERSON>’s primary election campaign (then the maximum amount permitted), <MONEY>$27,000</MONEY> to <PERSON>Trump</PERSON>’s general election campaign (also the maximum), and a total of <MONEY>$30,700</MONEY> to the <ORGANIZATION>Republican National Committee</ORGANIZATION> in <DATE>2016</DATE> alone,” the Beast reported. What’s more, <LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION> CEO <PERSON>Andy Techmanski</PERSON> is friends with <PERSON>Ryan Zinke</PERSON>, <PERSON>Trump</PERSON>’s secretary of the interior. (<LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION>’s headquarters are located in <PERSON>Zinke</PERSON>’s hometown.)

The inexperience of <LOCATION>Whitefish</LOCATION> and its connections with <PERSON>Trump</PERSON> are rightly raising suspicions about the company’s contract with <LOCATION>Puerto Rico</LOCATION>. But for the sake of the millions of people still living without power, let’s hope all of this fishiness is mere coincidence.

