<DATE>Seven months ago</DATE>, <NUMBER>three</NUMBER> employees of the <MISC>Ecuadorian</MISC> newspaper <ORGANIZATION>El Comercio</ORGANIZATION> were abducted in the <LOCATION>Mataje River</LOCATION> region on the border between <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION> and <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>. After almost <DURATION>three weeks</DURATION> in captivity, reporter <PERSON>Javier Ortega</PERSON>, photographer <PERSON>Paul Rivas</PERSON>, and their driver, <PERSON>Efrain Segarra</PERSON>, were executed by the <ORGANIZATION>Oliver Sinisterra Front</ORGANIZATION>, a group of former <ORGANIZATION>FARC</ORGANIZATION> guerillas and drug traffickers who operate in this lawless jungle. The murders punctuated a season of escalating violence, the likes of which <LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION> hasn’t seen in <DURATION>decades</DURATION>.

The official version of events remains full of inconsistencies, and the victims’ families are still waiting for answers. Why was a government representative dispatched to the border to await the journalists’ release, only to return empty-handed? Why was the <ORGANIZATION>El Comercio</ORGANIZATION> staff permitted in the area after <LOCATION>El Guacho</LOCATION>, the guerilla leader, had openly threatened civilians? The police could hardly feign ignorance: They had a secret communications channel with the rebels, and the transcripts clearly show their intentions.

An international team of more than <NUMBER>20</NUMBER> reporters, photojournalists, and videographers worked for <DURATION>four months</DURATION> to investigate the abduction and murder of their <MISC>Ecuadorian</MISC> colleagues, as well as to continue their reporting. <NUMBER>Six</NUMBER> organizations collaborated with OCCRP on the project: Fundacion para la Libertad de la Prensa (FLIP, <LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>), <PERSON>La Liga Contra El Silencio</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>), Periodistas sin Cadenas (<LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Fundamedios</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Ecuador</LOCATION>), <PERSON>Verdad Abierta</PERSON> (<LOCATION>Colombia</LOCATION>), and Forbidden Stories (<LOCATION>France</LOCATION>).

